On my desk in my office, I keep a small clay pot
أحتفظ على طاولة مكتبي بآنية فخارية
that I made in college. It's raku, which is a kind of pottery
صنعتها في الجامعة. تدعى "راكو"، هو نوع من الفخار
that began in Japan centuries ago as a way of
ظهر أول مرة باليابان منذ عصور، كطريقة
making bowls for the Japanese tea ceremony.
لصنع أواني طقوس الشاي اليابانية.
This one is more than 400 years old.
هذه عمرها أكثر من 400 سنة.
Each one was pinched or carved out of a ball of clay,
كل قطعة نحتت و شُكلت من كرة طين،
and it was the imperfections that people cherished.
وعيوبها كانت سبب إعجاب الناس بها.
Everyday pots like this cup take eight to 10 hours to fire.
يتطلب فنجان الإستخدام اليومي من 8 إلى 10 ساعات بالفرن.
I just took this out of the kiln last week, and the kiln itself
لقد أخذت هذه من الفرن الأسبوع الماضي، والفرن
takes another day or two to cool down, but raku
يحتاج ليوم أو يومين آخرين ليبرد، لكن "راكو"
is really fast. You do it outside, and you take the kiln
سريع للغاية، تصنعه خارج الفرن الذي يسخن
up to temperature. In 15 minutes, it goes to 1,500 degrees,
ل 1500 درجة خلال 15 دقيقة،
and as soon as you see that the glaze has melted inside,
وبمجرد أن تذوب الطبقة الزجاجية بالداخل
you can see that faint sheen, you turn the kiln off,
وتلاحظون بريق خافت، أطفئوا الفرن،
and you reach in with these long metal tongs,
وأدخلوا هذه الملاقيط المعدنية الطويلة،
you grab the pot, and in Japan, this red-hot pot
التقطوا الآنية. في اليابان يغمر الإناء المشتعل حمرة
would be immediately immersed in a solution of green tea,
مباشرة بمحلول من الشاي الأخضر،
and you can imagine what that steam would smell like.
ويمكنكم تخيل رائحة البخار.
But here in the United States, we ramp up the drama
أما هنا بالولايات المتحدة، نختصر الدراما
a little bit, and we drop our pots into sawdust,
نوعاً ما، فنقوم بتبريد الإناء بنشارة الخشب،
which catches on fire, and you take a garbage pail,
والتي تشتعل بسبب الحرارة، فنقوم
and you put it on top, and smoke starts pouring out.
بتغطيته بدلو للنفايات، ليبدأ الدخان بالتصاعد.
I would come home with my clothes reeking of woodsmoke.
فآعود للمنزل بملابس تفوح برائحة الخشب المحروق.
I love raku because it allows me to play with the elements.
أحب "راكو" لأنه يسمح لي باللعب بالعناصر.
I can shape a pot out of clay and choose a glaze,
يمكنني تشكيل آنية من الطين واختيار الطلاء،
but then I have to let it go to the fire and the smoke,
ولكن بعدها علي تركها في النار والدخان،
and what's wonderful is the surprises that happen,
والرائع فيه، هي المفاجآت التي تحدث،
like this crackle pattern, because it's really stressful
كهذا النمط المتشقق، فهو مثير للتوتر
on these pots. They go from 1,500 degrees
في هذه الأواني. وحرارتها تنزل من 1500 درجة
to room temperature in the space of just a minute.
إلى حرارة محيطها خلال دقيقة تقريباً.
Raku is a wonderful metaphor for the process of creativity.
"راكو" هو تعبير رائع عن عملية الإبداع.
I find in so many things that tension between
وجدت في الكثير من المجالات ذلك التجاذب بين
what I can control and what I have to let go
ما يمكنني التحكم به وما يجدر بي تركه يجري
happens all the time, whether I'm creating a new radio show
بحرية دائما، سواء عندما أبتكر برنامج إذاعي
or just at home negotiating with my teenage sons.
أو بالمنزل خلال نقاشي مع أبنائي المراهقين.
When I sat down to write a book about creativity,
عندما جلست لكتابة كتاب عن الإبداع،
I realized that the steps were reversed.
تنبهت إلى أن المراحل كانت معكوسة.
I had to let go at the very beginning, and I had to
كان علي التخلي عن التحكم منذ البداية،
immerse myself in the stories of hundreds of artists
وأن أغرق نفسي بقصص المئات من الفنانين
and writers and musicians and filmmakers, and as I listened
والكتاب والموسيقيين والمخرجين، وباستماعي
to these stories, I realized that creativity
لتلك القصص، أدركت أن الإبداع
grows out of everyday experiences
يولد من التجارب اليومية
more often than you might think, including
أكثر مما نعتقد، بما في ذلك
letting go.
التخلي عن التحكم.
It was supposed to break, but that's okay. (Laughter) (Laughs)
كان من المفترض أن ينكسر، لكنه لم يفعل. (ضحك) (ضحك)
That's part of the letting go, is sometimes it happens
هذا جزء من التخلي عن التحكم، فقد تحدث أحيانا
and sometimes it doesn't, because creativity also grows
وفي أخرى لا تحدث، لأن الإبداع يولد أيضا
from the broken places.
من الإنكسارات.
The best way to learn about anything
القصص هي أفضل طريقة لتعلم أي شيء،
is through stories, and so I want to tell you a story
لذلك أود أن أحكي لكم قصة
about work and play and about four aspects of life
حول العمل واللعب وحول 4 جوانب للحياة
that we need to embrace
نحن بحاجة لتبنيها
in order for our own creativity to flourish.
حتى يزدهر إبداعنا.
The first embrace is something that we think,
أول شئ يجعلنا نقول،
"Oh, this is very easy," but it's actually getting harder,
"ما أسهل هذا،" ولكن إنه أصبح أصعب حالياً،
and that's paying attention to the world around us.
وهذا هو الإنتباه للعالم من حولنا.
So many artists speak about needing to be open,
الكثير من الفنانين يتحدثون عن الحاجة لأن نكون منفتحين،
to embrace experience, and that's hard to do when
لعيش التجربة، والقيام بهذا صعب عندما
you have a lighted rectangle in your pocket that
يكون لديكم مستطيل مضيء في جيبكم
takes all of your focus.
لأنه سيستحوذ على كل تركيزكم.
The filmmaker Mira Nair speaks about growing up
تتحدث المخرجة ميرا نير عن نشأتها
in a small town in India. Its name is Bhubaneswar,
بمدينة صغيرة بالهند تدعى بوبانسوار
and here's a picture of one of the temples in her town.
وهذه صورة لأحد معابد مدينتها.
Mira Nair: In this little town, there were like 2,000 temples.
ميرا نير: كانت بهذه المدينة الصغيرة حوالي 2000 معبد.
We played cricket all the time. We kind of grew up
كنا نلعب الكريكت دائما. نحن نوعا ما
in the rubble. The major thing that inspired me,
كبرنا بين الأنقاض. أكبر شيء ألهمني،
that led me on this path, that made me a filmmaker eventually,
وقادني في هذا الطريق، وجعلني بالنهاية مخرجة،
was traveling folk theater that would come through the town
هو المسرح الشعبي المتجول الذي مر من المدينة
and I would go off and see these great battles
فكنت أخرج وأشاهد تلك الملاحم
of good and evil by two people in a school field
بين الخير والشر يؤديها شخصين بساحة المدرسة
with no props but with a lot of, you know,
دون أي أكسسوارات ولكن بشغف،
passion, and hashish as well, and it was amazing.
ومخدر الحشيش أيضا، وكان ذلك رائعا.
You know, the folk tales of Mahabharata and Ramayana,
كالقصص الشعبية لماهابهاراتا ورامايانا،
the two holy books, the epics that everything comes out of
الكتابين المقدسين، الملاحم التي ينبع منها
in India, they say. After seeing that Jatra, the folk theater,
كل شيء بالهند، كما يقولون.بعد مشاهدة جاترا أو المسرح الشعبي،
I knew I wanted to get on, you know, and perform.
علمت أني أريد المشاركة والتمثيل.
Julie Burstein: Isn't that a wonderful story?
جولي بورستين: أليست قصة رائعة؟
You can see the sort of break in the everyday.
قد تمرون بلحظات صدق مع النفس في أي يوم.
There they are in the school fields, but it's good and evil,
جميعهم هنا بساحة المدرسة، ولكن الخير والشر،
and passion and hashish. And Mira Nair was a young girl
والشغف والحشيش. وميرا نير كانت ما تزال طفلة
with thousands of other people watching this performance,
مع المئات من الأشخاص الآخرين يشاهدون تلك المسرحية،
but she was ready. She was ready to open up
ولكنها كانت مستعدة. كانت مستعدة للانفتاح
to what it sparked in her, and it led her,
على الشرارة التي اتقدت داخلها والتي قادتها،
as she said, down this path to become
كما تقول، للسير بهذا الطريق لتصبح
an award-winning filmmaker.
مخرجة حائزة على جوائز.
So being open for that experience that might change you
الانفتاح على التجربة التي قد تغيرك
is the first thing we need to embrace.
هو أول شيء يجب أن نتبناه.
Artists also speak about how some of their most powerful work
الفنانين أيضا يتحدثون كيف أن بعض أقوى أعمالهم
comes out of the parts of life that are most difficult.
استوحوها من نواحي الحياة الصعبة.
The novelist Richard Ford speaks about
يتحدث الروائي ريتشارد فورد عن
a childhood challenge that continues to be something
واحدة من تحديات طفولته التي مازال
he wrestles with today. He's severely dyslexic.
يصارعها حتى اليوم. وهو عسر قراءة شديد.
Richard Ford: I was slow to learn to read, went all the way
ريتشارد فورد: كنت بطيء التعلم والقراءة، خلال مساري
through school not really reading more than the minimum,
الدراسي لم أقرأ أكثر من الحد الأدنى،
and still to this day can't read silently
ومازلت حتى اليوم لا أستطيع القراءة صامتاً
much faster than I can read aloud,
أسرع بكثير من قراءتي بالجهر،
but there were a lot of benefits to being dyslexic for me
ولكن كوني مصاب بعسر القراءة كان شيئا مفيدا لي
because when I finally did reconcile myself to how slow
ففي النهاية عندما اعتادت نفسي البطء
I was going to have to do it, then I think I came very slowly
الذي كان علي القراءة به، أعتقد أني شيئا فشيئا
into an appreciation of all of those qualities of language
بدأت أدرك كل مميزات اللغة
and of sentences that are not just the cognitive
والجمل التي لا تنحصر فقط بالجانب الإدراكي
aspects of language: the syncopations, the sounds of words,
باللغة: الوتيرة أو أصوات الكلمات،
what words look like, where paragraphs break,
شكل الكلمات وحيث تقف الفقرات،
where lines break. I mean, I wasn't so badly dyslexic that
أين تنتهي السطور. أعني، لم أكن مصاب بعسر قراءة شديد
I was disabled from reading. I just had to do it
لكي لا أتمكن من القراءة. كان فقط علي القيام بذلك
really slowly, and as I did, lingering on those sentences
ببطء شديد، وكما أفعل، بالانكباب المطول على الجمل
as I had to linger, I fell heir to language's other qualities,
بالشكل الكافي، بدأت أشعر أني أرث ميزات أخرى للغة،
which I think has helped me write sentences.
والتي أعتقد أنها ساعدتني على كتابة الجمل.
JB: It's so powerful. Richard Ford, who's won the Pulitzer Prize,
هذا مذهل. ريتشارد فورد، الفائز بجائزة بوليتزر،
says that dyslexia helped him write sentences.
قال أن عسر القراءة ساعده على كتابة الجمل.
He had to embrace this challenge, and I use that word
كان عليه تبنى هذا التحدي، وأستخدم هذه الكلمة
intentionally. He didn't have to overcome dyslexia.
عن قصد. لم يكن عليه تخطي عسر القراءة.
He had to learn from it. He had to learn to hear the music
كان عليه التعلم منها. وأن يقرأ ويسمع الموسيقى
in language.
في اللغة.
Artists also speak about how pushing up against
يتحدث الفنانون أيضا عن الوصول
the limits of what they can do, sometimes pushing
لحدود ما يمكنهم فعله، بل أحيانا
into what they can't do, helps them focus
إلى حد ما لا يستطيعون فعله، ما يساعدهم على التركيز
on finding their own voice.
لإيجاد صوتهم الخاص.
The sculptor Richard Serra talks about how,
يتحدث النحات ريتشارد سييرا مبيناً،
as a young artist, he thought he was a painter,
أنه عندما كان فنانا شابا، كان يرى نفسه رساما،
and he lived in Florence after graduate school.
وعاش في فلورنسا بعد تخرجه من الجامعة.
While he was there, he traveled to Madrid,
خلال تلك الفترة سافر إلى مدريد،
where he went to the Prado to see this picture
حيث ذهب لمتحف ديل برادو لرؤية لوحة
by the Spanish painter Diego Velázquez.
للرسام الإسباني دييغو فيلاثكيث.
It's from 1656, and it's called "Las Meninas,"
رسمها في 1656 وتدعى "لاس مينيناس،"
and it's the picture of a little princess
وهي صورة لأميرات صغيرات
and her ladies-in-waiting, and if you look over
ووصيفاتهن، وإن تمعنتم خلف
that little blonde princess's shoulder, you'll see a mirror,
كتف الأميرة الصغيرة الشقراء، يمكنكم رؤية مرآة
and reflected in it are her parents, the King and Queen
تعكس والديها، ملك وملكة
of Spain, who would be standing where you might stand
إسبانيا، الذين ربما يقفان حيث تقفون أنتم
to look at the picture.
للنظر إلى الصورة.
As he often did, Velázquez put himself in this painting too.
كما كان يفعل غالبا، وضع فيلاثكيث نفسه أيضا بالصورة.
He's standing on the left with his paintbrush in one hand
إنه يقف في اليسار مع ريشته في يد
and his palette in the other.
ولوحة الألوان بالأخرى
Richard Serra: I was standing there looking at it,
ريتشارد سيرا: كنت أقف هناك أنظر إليها،
and I realized that Velázquez was looking at me,
وأدركت أن فيلاثكيث كان ينظر إلي،
and I thought, "Oh. I'm the subject of the painting."
فقلت لنفسي، "أنا موضوع الصورة!"
And I thought, "I'm not going to be able to do that painting."
وفكرت،"لن أكون قادرا على رسم مثل هذه الصورة."
I was to the point where I was using a stopwatch
وصلت إلى درجة أني استخدمت ساعة التوقيف
and painting squares out of randomness,
ورسمت مربعات بشكل عشوائي،
and I wasn't getting anywhere. So I went back and dumped
لم استطع انجاز شئ ، لذا عدت
all my paintings in the Arno, and I thought, I'm going to just start playing around.
ورميت كل لوحاتي بنهر أرنو، فقلت لنفسي، سأبدأ باللعب فقط.
JB: Richard Serra says that so nonchalantly, you might
قالها رتشارد سيرا بلا مبالاة، قد تكون
have missed it. He went and saw this painting by a guy
مرت عليكم مرور الكرام. ذهب وشاهد هذه اللوحة لشخص
who'd been dead for 300 years, and realized,
توفي منذ 300 سنة، وأدرك،
"I can't do that," and so Richard Serra went back
"لا أستطيع القيام بذلك،" وعاد ريتشارد سيرا
to his studio in Florence, picked up all of his work
إلى مرسمه بفلورنسا، جمع كل أعماله
up to that point, and threw it in a river.
التي رسمها حتى ذلك الوقت، ورماها بنهر.
Richard Serra let go of painting at that moment,
في ذلك الوقت ترك ريتشارد سيرا الرسم
but he didn't let go of art. He moved to New York City,
ولكن لم يترك الفن. ورحل إلى نيويورك،
and he put together a list of verbs
ووضع قائمة أفعال
— to roll, to crease, to fold —
-- لفَّ، جَعَّدَ، ثَنْي --
more than a hundred of them, and as he said,
أكثر من مائة فعل، وكما قال،
he just started playing around. He did these things
لقد بدء فقط باللعب. فبدأ يطبق هذ الأفعال
to all kinds of material. He would take a huge sheet of lead
على كل أنواع المواد. أخذ صفيحة من الرصاص
and roll it up and unroll it. He would do the same thing
ولفها ثم فكها. وقام بنفس الشيء
to rubber, and when he got to the direction "to lift,"
بالمطاط، وعندما وصل إلى "رفع،" ابتكر التالي،
he created this, which is in the Museum of Modern Art.
والموجود بمتحف الفنون المعاصر.
Richard Serra had to let go of painting
كان على ريتشارد سيرا أن يترك الرسم
in order to embark on this playful exploration
ليبدأ في هذا الاستكشاف الممتع
that led him to the work that he's known for today:
والذي قاده إلى العمل الذي جعله مشهورا اليوم:
huge curves of steel that require our time and motion
تلك المنحنيات الضخمة من الصلب التي تتطلب
to experience. In sculpture,
وقتنا ومشاعرنا للتجربة. في النحت،
Richard Serra is able to do what he couldn't do in painting.
ريتشارد قادر على فعل ما لا يستطيعه في الرسم.
He makes us the subject of his art.
إنه يجعل منا نحن موضوعا لفنه.
So experience and challenge
إذا التجربة والتحدي
and limitations are all things we need to embrace
والحدود هي كل ما نحتاج تبنيه
for creativity to flourish.
ليزدهر الإبداع.
There's a fourth embrace, and it's the hardest.
وهناك متبنى رابع ،وهو الأصعب.
It's the embrace of loss,
هو تبني الخسارة،
the oldest and most constant of human experiences.
المرافق الأقدم و الدائم لتجارب الإنسان.
In order to create, we have to stand in that space
في الطريق للإبداع، يجب أن نقف في تلك المساحة
between what we see in the world and what we hope for,
بين ما نراه في العالم وما نأمله،
looking squarely at rejection, at heartbreak,
مواجهة الرفض، والحسرة،
at war, at death.
في الحرب، وفي الموت.
That's a tough space to stand in.
وهذا مكان من الصعب الوقوف به.
The educator Parker Palmer calls it "the tragic gap,"
يسميه المربي باركر بالمر "الفجوة المأساوية،"
tragic not because it's sad but because it's inevitable,
هي مأساوية ليس لأنها محزنة بل لأنها حتمية،
and my friend Dick Nodel likes to say,
ويحب صديقي ديك نودل أن يقول،
"You can hold that tension like a violin string
"يمكنك التحكم بهذا التوتر كما توزن أوتار الكمان
and make something beautiful."
لتعطي شيئا جميلا."
That tension resonates in the work of the photographer
وأصداء هذا التوتر تتجلى في عمل المصور
Joel Meyerowitz, who at the beginning of his career was
جويل مايروتز، الذي عرف منذ بداية مسيرته
known for his street photography, for capturing a moment
بتصوير الشارع، و التقاط اللحظات
on the street, and also for his beautiful photographs
في الشارع، وكذا لصوره الرائعة
of landscapes -- of Tuscany, of Cape Cod,
للمناظر الطبيعية -- لتوسكانا، وكيب كود،
of light.
وللضوء.
Joel is a New Yorker, and his studio for many years
جويل من نيويورك، وكان له استوديو بحي تشيلسي
was in Chelsea, with a straight view downtown
لسنوات، بإطلالة مباشرة على مركز التجارة العالمي
to the World Trade Center, and he photographed
بوسط المدينة، وقد صور
those buildings in every sort of light.
تلك المباني تحت كل أنواع الإضاءة.
You know where this story goes.
وتعلمون إلى أين ستأخذنا هذه القصة.
On 9/11, Joel wasn't in New York. He was out of town,
في 11/9 لم يكن جويل بنيويورك. كان خارجها.
but he raced back to the city, and raced down to the site
لكنه عاد بسرعة إلى المدينة، وأسرع نحو موقع
of the destruction.
الدمار.
Joel Meyerowitz: And like all the other passersby,
جويل مايروتز: وككل المارة
I stood outside the chain link fence on Chambers
وقفت خلف حاجز الحماية بشارع تشامبر
and Greenwich, and all I could see was the smoke
وغرينتش، وكل ما استطعت رؤيته هو دخان
and a little bit of rubble, and I raised my camera
وبعض الأنقاض، فرفعت مصورتي
to take a peek, just to see if there was something to see,
لإلقاء نظرة، فقط لرؤية إن كان هناك شيء،
and some cop, a lady cop, hit me on my shoulder,
فضربتني شرطية على كتفي،
and said, "Hey, no pictures!"
قائلة: "لا صور!"
And it was such a blow that it woke me up,
وكانت ضربة جعلتني أستيقظ،
in the way that it was meant to be, I guess.
وأعتقد، أنه كان هدفها.
And when I asked her why no pictures, she said,
وعندما سألتها لم لا أصور، قالت،
"It's a crime scene. No photographs allowed."
"هذه ساحة جريمة. التصوير ممنوع."
And I asked her, "What would happen if I was a member
وسألتها: "وماذا إن كنت مصورا صحفيا؟"
of the press?" And she told me,
فردت قائلة،
"Oh, look back there," and back a block was the press corps
"إذا أنظر هناك،" بالخلف كانت هناك مجموعة من الصحفيين
tied up in a little penned-in area,
مجتمعين بمكان مخصص لهم،
and I said, "Well, when do they go in?"
فقلت: "متى سيدخلون إلى هناك؟"
and she said, "Probably never."
فردت: "على الأرجح لن يفعلوا."
And as I walked away from that, I had this crystallization,
وبينما أنا أبتعد من هناك إذا بشيء يلمع بذهني
probably from the blow, because it was an insult in a way.
ربما بسبب الضربة، لأنها نوعا ما كانت إهانة.
I thought, "Oh, if there's no pictures,
ففكرت، "إن لم يكن هناك صور،
then there'll be no record. We need a record."
فلن يكون هناك ذاكرة. ونحن بحاجة لذاكرة."
And I thought, "I'm gonna make that record.
وفكرت، "أنا سأترك تلك الذاكرة.
I'll find a way to get in, because I don't want to
سأجد طريقة لأدخل لهناك، لأنني لا أريد
see this history disappear."
أن أشاهد هذا التاريخ يختفي."
JB: He did. He pulled in every favor he could,
لقد فعل. استخدم كل علاقاته،
and got a pass into the World Trade Center site,
وحصل على إذن بالدخول لمركز التجارة العالمي،
where he photographed for nine months almost every day.
حيث صوره لمدة تسعة أشهر وبشكل يومي تقريبا.
Looking at these photographs today brings back
النظر إلى تلك الصور اليوم يذكرني
the smell of smoke that lingered on my clothes
برائحة الدخان العالقة بملابسي
when I went home to my family at night.
عندما عدت إلى منزلي وأسرتي ليلا.
My office was just a few blocks away.
كان مكتبي قريبا.
But some of these photographs are beautiful,
ولكن بعض هذه الصور رائعة.
and we wondered, was it difficult for Joel Meyerowitz
فنتساءل، هل كان من الصعب على جويل مايروتز
to make such beauty out of such devastation?
لاستخراج كل هذا الجمال من كل هذا الدمار؟
JM: Well, you know, ugly, I mean, powerful
كان ذلك قبيحا، أقصد قويا
and tragic and horrific and everything, but
ومأساويا ومروعا وما إلى ذلك، لكن
it was also as, in nature, an enormous event
كان أيضا كما في الطبيعة، حدث ضخم
that was transformed after the fact into this residue,
تحول في نهاية الحدث إلى هذه الأنقاض.
and like many other ruins
وكالعديد من الأنقاض
— you go to the ruins of the Colosseum or the ruins of a cathedral someplace —
- تذهبون إلى أنقاض الكولوسيوم أو كنيسة في مكان ما-
and they take on a new meaning when you watch the weather.
لكنها تكتسي معنى جديا بحسب الطقس الذي تشاهدونها فيه.
I mean, there were afternoons I was down there,
أقصد كنت أذهب هناك كل ظهيرة،
and the light goes pink and there's a mist in the air
حيث يصبح الأفق ورديا مع القليل من الضباب
and you're standing in the rubble, and I found myself
وأنا واقف بين الأنقاض، أجد نفسي
recognizing both the inherent beauty of nature
أمام الجمال الخلاب للطبيعة
and the fact that nature, as time,
وحقيقة أن الطبيعة بمساعدة الوقت،
is erasing this wound.
ستشفي هذا الجرح.
Time is unstoppable, and it transforms the event.
لا يمكن إيقاف الوقت، وهو يغير الأحداث.
It gets further and further away from the day,
فهو يحملنا أبعد فأبعد عن ذلك اليوم،
and light and seasons temper it in some way,
والضوء والفصول تيسر ذلك نوعا ما.
and it's not that I'm a romantic. I'm really a realist.
وليس ذلك لأني رومنسي. بل أنا واقعي.
The reality is, there's the Woolworth Building
فالحقيقة هي، هذا هو مبنى وولوورث
in a veil of smoke from the site, but it's now like a scrim
مغطى بستار من دخان الموقع، ولكنه الآن كشاش
across a theater, and it's turning pink,
فوق مسرح وهو يتحول للون وردي،
you know, and down below there are hoses spraying,
وأسفله هناك خراطيم ترش المياه ،
and the lights have come on for the evening, and the water
وتضاء الأنوار مساء، والماء
is turning acid green because the sodium lamps are on,
يكتسي لونا أخضر بسبب مصابيح الصوديوم،
and I'm thinking, "My God, who could dream this up?"
ففكرت، "ياإلهي، من كان ليتخيل هذا؟"
But the fact is, I'm there, it looks like that,
ولكن الواقع أني هناك وهذا ما بدا عليه الموقع
you have to take a picture.
ومن الواجب التقاط صورة له.
JB: You have to take a picture. That sense of urgency,
عليك التقاط صورة. هذا معنى الضرورة،
of the need to get to work, is so powerful in Joel's story.
الحاجة للقيام بالعمل، هي قوية في قصة جويل.
When I saw Joel Meyerowitz recently, I told him how much
عندما التقيت مؤخرا جويل مايروتز، أخبرته
I admired his passionate obstinacy, his determination
كم أعجبت بعناده القوي وتصميمه
to push through all the bureaucratic red tape to get to work,
على تخطي كل عوائق البيروقراطية للقيام بعمله،
and he laughed, and he said, "I'm stubborn,
وقد ضحك وقال: "أنا عنيد،
but I think what's more important
ولكن أعتقد أن الأهم
is my passionate optimism."
هو تفاؤلي الشديد."
The first time I told these stories, a man in the audience
في أول مرة أخبرت بهذه القصص، رفع رجل من
raised his hand and said, "All these artists talk about
الحضور يده وقال: "كل هؤلاء الفنانين تحدثوا عن
their work, not their art, which has got me thinking about
عملهم وليس فنهم ما جعلني أفكر
my work and where the creativity is there,
بعملي وعن مكان الإبداع المتواجد به،
and I'm not an artist." He's right. We all wrestle
وأنا لست فنانا." إنه محق. كلنا نكافح
with experience and challenge, limits and loss.
بتجاربنا وتحدياتنا وحدود قدراتنا وأحزاننا.
Creativity is essential to all of us,
الإبداع شيء أساسي لكل واحد منا
whether we're scientists or teachers,
سواء كنا علماء أو مدرسين
parents or entrepreneurs.
أو آباء أو رجال أعمال.
I want to leave you with another
أود أن أترككم مع صورة أخرى
image of a Japanese tea bowl. This one
لآنية تستخدم بطقس الشاي الياباني
is at the Freer Gallery in Washington, D.C.
وتوجد بمعرض فرير بوشنطن العاصمة،
It's more than a hundred years old and you can still see
عمرها أكثر من مائة عام ويمكنكم مشاهدة
the fingermarks where the potter pinched it.
بصمات الصانع حيث ضغطها.
But as you can also see, this one did break
لكن كما تشاهدون فهذه قد انكسرت
at some point in its hundred years.
خلال وقت ما في المائة عام من عمرها.
But the person who put it back together,
لكن الشخص الذي رممها،
instead of hiding the cracks,
عوضاً أن يخفي الشقوق،
decided to emphasize them, using gold lacquer to repair it.
قرر أن يبرزها ، باستخدام صمغ ذهبي لترميمها.
This bowl is more beautiful now, having been broken,
أصبحت هذه الآنية أكثر جمالا عندما انكسرت
than it was when it was first made,
مما كانت عليه عند صنعها،
and we can look at those cracks, because
ويمكننا مشاهدة شقوقها، لأنها
they tell the story that we all live,
تخبرنا عن القصة التي نحياها جميعا،
of the cycle of creation and destruction,
عن دورة الخلق والتدمير،
of control and letting go, of picking up the pieces
عن التحكم وترك الأمور تجري بحرية،
and making something new.
عن تجميع الشظايا لخلق شيء ما جديد.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكر لكم. (تصفيق)